<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-19T18:24:59-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">xing liu ∧ 刘行</title><subtitle>local thoughtspace of a possible boltzmann brain in awe of the cosmic infinite</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The background of the universe</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/astro/2023/12/19/medium.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The background of the universe" /><published>2023-12-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/astro/2023/12/19/medium</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/astro/2023/12/19/medium.html">&lt;p&gt;When we try to picture the cosmos, we tend to only think about the shiny stuff — 
stars, galaxies, and very very hungry black holes. But stars could not burn without hydrogen to collapse from,
galaxies could not coalesce without dark matter to attract the stars, and black holes cannot shine without gas and dust to feed on.
The background medium, as it turns out, has as much importance to astronomy as the objects under the spotlights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with our home galaxy, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milky_Way&quot;&gt;Milky Way&lt;/a&gt;. 
There are approximately a hundred billion (10¹¹) stars bound in its gravitational system, 
collectively weighing around 10¹¹ Suns (our Sun is pretty average — probably &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stellar_classification&quot;&gt;G tier&lt;/a&gt;). 
According to our current model of stellar evolution, 
every single one of them started out as a loose (one might even say &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nebula&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;nebulous&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) cloud of gas and dust,
contracting for millions of years until their core reaches the critical temperature for nuclear fusion to occur. Then, after anywhere
from millions to billions of years, they exhaust all their fuel, and through either a gentle winding-down or a spectacular explosion,
return most of their matter back into the medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the births and deaths of stars roughly balance, it leaves around 10¹¹ Suns’ worth of gas and dust hanging around inside the galaxy,
on the same order of magnitude as the collective mass of the stars themselves. 
As expected, we mainly find those gas and dust in the thin, flat central slice of the Milky Way disk, which is also where most of the young stars live.
(Including our Sun, which explains why we can’t really see the center of our galaxy — the pesky dust blocks the line of sight.)
Its cosmic cycle between loosely-bound clouds and dense, burning stars forms the basis of the galactic ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have stars, we need a way to put them into a galaxy. 
You might think that, mirroring our Sun’s role in the solar system, 
having a super massive black hole at the galactic center would be enough to hold everything together.
Unfortunately, Sagitarrius A*, the super massive black hole in the core of the Milky Way, just isn’t supermassive enough!
While the Sun holds over 99.8% of the mass of the solar system, 
Sagitarrius A*, weighing at a measly several million Suns, is less than 0.01% of the mass of the Milky Way.
Adding the bulge of stars, gas, and dust clustered around Sag A* doesn’t make that big of a dent either.
For galaxies to form, there has to be a lot of extra mass concentrated near the center that we’ve so far not accounted for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the stuff we call &lt;em&gt;dark matter&lt;/em&gt;. We don’t really know what it’s made of, but for it to hold galaxies together
and explain a bunch of other cosmological mysteries, we know it has to satisify a few properties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;em&gt;interstellar medium&lt;/em&gt; (ISM) — the stuff between stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s just the stuff inside galaxies. If the distance between neighboring stars is vast 
(it takes light more than 4 years to travel from here to Alpha Centauri), 
the distance between neighboring galaxies is truly cosmic. And between galaxy neighborhoods? incomprehensible.
Inside galaxies, the medium and the stars are roughly balanced. Out in the intergalactic wilderness, the wispy medium is nearly all there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as there’s far more grass on the plains than sheep, and far more water in the seas than fish, the full background 
medium of the universe actually far, &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; outweighs the stars! 
We believe as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This medium contains loose gas, dust, and most mysteriously, &lt;em&gt;dark matter&lt;/em&gt;. (more to come)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="astro" /><summary type="html">When we try to picture the cosmos, we tend to only think about the shiny stuff — stars, galaxies, and very very hungry black holes. But stars could not burn without hydrogen to collapse from, galaxies could not coalesce without dark matter to attract the stars, and black holes cannot shine without gas and dust to feed on. The background medium, as it turns out, has as much importance to astronomy as the objects under the spotlights.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">December 2023</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/monthly/2023/12/18/monthly.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="December 2023" /><published>2023-12-18T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/monthly/2023/12/18/monthly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/monthly/2023/12/18/monthly.html">&lt;p&gt;decision paralysis but also, &lt;br /&gt;
recognizing in a finite lifespan I &lt;br /&gt;
get to pick a few things out of an &lt;br /&gt;
infinitude to savor is kinda neat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;如果有桂花吃、白兰花闻，世界就好了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;current trajectory: physics &amp;gt; cosmology/particle &amp;gt; theoretical/computational&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deniz Türker. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psupress.org/books/titles/978-0-271-09391-8.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Accidental Palace: The Making of Yıldız in Nineteenth-Century Istanbul&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The residence of the last Ottoman sultan before his empire’s fall.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Tong. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.damtp.cam.ac.uk/user/tong/gaugetheory.html&quot;&gt;“Lecture notes on Gauge Theory.”&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Every once in a while, I try to get a glimpse of some topic years beyond my current level of understanding. 
Two years ago it was general relativity, last summer it was inflationary cosmology, and last week it was gauge theory 
— basically, fields in which the concepts and equations nearly completely lose me. 
Even though I am not really ready to efficiently learn these topics, I think it’s helpful to have a somewhat tangible sense of the long road ahead.
With this goal in mind, I began reading and promptly lost myself by the second chapter.
I did manage to make a video out of it though.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matthew McQuinn. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-astro-082214-122355&quot;&gt;“The Evolution of the Intergalactic Medium.”&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When we try to picture the cosmos, we tend to only think about the shiny stuff — 
stars, galaxies, and very very hungry black holes. But stars could not burn without hydrogen to collapse from,
galaxies could not coalesce without dark matter to attract the stars, and black holes cannot shine without gas and dust to feed on.
The background medium, as it turns out, has as much importance to astronomy as the objects under the spotlights.
I wrote a more layperson explanation of the above in &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/astro/2023/12/19/medium.html&quot;&gt;“The stuff between all the universe’s bright lights.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cade Metz et al. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/12/03/technology/ai-openai-musk-page-altman.html&quot;&gt;“Ego, Fear and Money: How the A.I. Fuse Was Lit”&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;These people have strange sights for the future.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="monthly" /><summary type="html">decision paralysis but also, recognizing in a finite lifespan I get to pick a few things out of an infinitude to savor is kinda neat</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A rough sketch of gauge theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/physics/animation/2023/12/08/gauge.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A rough sketch of gauge theory" /><published>2023-12-08T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/physics/animation/2023/12/08/gauge</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/physics/animation/2023/12/08/gauge.html">&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vEN4uXE8rkg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very rough introduction to one of the building blocks of modern theoretical particle physics,
starting with its humble origins in the field of classical electrodynamics, 
and showing how this almost “redundant” description of electromagnetism 
grew into the language with which physicists think about the fundamental nature of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="physics" /><category term="animation" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">November 2023</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/monthly/2023/11/20/monthly.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="November 2023" /><published>2023-11-20T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/monthly/2023/11/20/monthly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/monthly/2023/11/20/monthly.html">&lt;p&gt;in summary, month of reading too many things&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;red,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helliwell &amp;amp; Sahakian. Modern Classical Mechanics.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;God-tier capstone chapters offering us lowly undergrads glimpses of quantum path integrals, gauge invariance, perturbation theory, among other &lt;em&gt;fascinating&lt;/em&gt; areas of modern physics&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lindner. A Complete Guide to Theoretical Physics.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The promise in the title is the allure.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leslie Pierce. The Imperial Harem: Women and sovereignty in the Ottoman Empire.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The struggles for power never bores&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Benjamin Fortna. Imperial Classrooms: Islam, the State, and Education in the Late Ottoman Empire.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Maps!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Benedict Anderson. Imagined Communities.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The&lt;/strong&gt; book on nationalism.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amy Tan. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2000/12/25/immortal-heart&quot;&gt;“Immortal Heart”&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Read it on the night bart from San Jose back to Berkeley. How little time I’m devoting to fiction!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thomas Mallon. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2023/11/27/yesterday-a-new-history-of-nostalgia-tobias-becker-book-review&quot;&gt;“What if Nostalgia Isn’t What It Used to Be?”&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="monthly" /><summary type="html">in summary, month of reading too many things</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes on Carroll &amp;amp; Ostlie, Introduction to Modern Astrophysics, parts I &amp;amp; II</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/notes/astro/2023/07/20/notes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Carroll &amp;amp; Ostlie, Introduction to Modern Astrophysics, parts I &amp;amp; II" /><published>2023-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/notes/astro/2023/07/20/notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/notes/astro/2023/07/20/notes.html">&lt;p&gt;My notes for the first two parts of Carroll &amp;amp; Ostlie’s “Big Orange Book”, 
written in a combination of markdown and LaTeX for the optimal mix of 
accessibility and mathematical typographic beauty, are available at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://xingyzt.net/notes/intro-to-modern-astrophysics&quot;&gt;xingyzt.net/notes/intro-to-modern-astrophysics&lt;/a&gt;. 
Enjoy studying the universe!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="notes" /><category term="astro" /><summary type="html">My notes for the first two parts of Carroll &amp;amp; Ostlie’s “Big Orange Book”, written in a combination of markdown and LaTeX for the optimal mix of accessibility and mathematical typographic beauty, are available at xingyzt.net/notes/intro-to-modern-astrophysics. Enjoy studying the universe!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">{}</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/story/2023/02/13/set.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="{}" /><published>2023-02-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-02-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/story/2023/02/13/set</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/story/2023/02/13/set.html">&lt;p&gt;They call the piece a Set, the basic boundary between an Inside and an Outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to tell the creation story of numbers, something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let a Set which bounds nothing and excludes everything be named Zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let every Set after it bind together the preceding Set, and a Set of the preceding Set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this simple duet, a floodgate to the Naturals opens. One is the Set which bounds the Zero; Two is the set which bounds Zero, One, and Two. So on and so forth. A countable infinity of numerals, each unique and orderable, born from drawing boundaries between Insides and Outs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the Negatives, first examine their true nature: the difference between two naturals. To make Negative One, bind together One and Two, or Two and Three, or Three and Four… The floodgates now point in two directions, and the Integers were born.
.
Rationals are pairs of Integers, bound in fractions. Half is One and Two, or Two and Four, or Three and Six… The steppes of numbers become smooth slopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reals are harder to define: A pair of two infinite sets of Rationals, one binding all that’s less than the Real, the other binding all that’s more. They race like Zeno towards each other, converging from opposite ends, Negative and Positive Infinities, after an eternity, onto their final destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pair the two Reals, and out come the Complexes. Pair four, Quaternions. Pair every number in an infinity of them to another to get maps and functions. Flip the definitions on their heads to get p-adic numbers, a separate breed of beasts who behave like nothing else. From a set, a universe.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="story" /><summary type="html">They call the piece a Set, the basic boundary between an Inside and an Outside.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Polarizar: Visual odometry for the 2023 FTC robotics competition</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/code/robotics/2023/02/12/polarizar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Polarizar: Visual odometry for the 2023 FTC robotics competition" /><published>2023-02-12T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-02-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/code/robotics/2023/02/12/polarizar</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/code/robotics/2023/02/12/polarizar.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problem: Our robot needs to precisely navigate a field of poles.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video controls=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;720&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;/media/polarizar-w720.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Odometry is a critical component of any fast and precise Autonomous program. In designing our Autonomous strategy, we considered several conventional means of odometry, but discarded every single one for their flaws: Inertial Measurement Units suffer from significant drift during integration; Encoder odometry can be very precise on the short scales, but lack the accuracy for navigating around multiple poles; And while distance sensors can detect poles to high precision, they lack a wide field of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, we decided to explore visual odometry instead, which allows our robot to know its position and orientation on the field from the camera alone. This approach is especially useful for this FTC season due to the lattice of highly visible poles on the field. The plan was this: track the positions of poles in the camera, convert them into coordinates on the field, and from them, compute the motion of the robot. In between poles, encoders can then provide more precise positions on top of visual odometry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because our specific pole recognition odometry strategy was, as far as we know, completely novel, we embarked on this project with low-level OpenCV. We first prototyped programs in Python on laptop, which was faster to debug and iterate. Our first experiment was determining the positions of cones on a table from a laptop camera: He learned to project the table onto a plane, then isolate the colors to find the centers of red and blue contours, producing accurate positions for the cones. We then applied the technique to the field: Isolating the yellow poles and projecting their lowest points onto a square plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We first planned to calculate the robot’s motion from the relative frame-by-frame changes in each pole’s position. However, this approach faced IMU-like integration drift over time: if the robot moved in a circle, its calculated position would not end up where it started. After a divine revelation from semi-nude men, we realized we could measure the poles’ absolute position from “ground-truth” measurements instead: This was not easy, because only two to three poles are visible in our off-the-shelf webcam, so there is little data to match them with the 18 ground-truth poles. However, past position estimates can crudely align them closely enough to match and calculate the absolute difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the algorithm in its entirety: First, we identify the poles by color. Then, we project them onto a field-sized square plane. Next, we shift them by the last estimated robot position to match them with the absolute positions of the ground-truth poles. Finally, we calculate the difference to update the estimated robot position. Because this approach always measures against the ground truth, errors do not accumulate over time. There is noise from camera shakes and uncertain pole identification, but as long as two or more poles stay in the field of view at all times, we can obtain an accurate position of the robot from the camera alone, and the average error stays constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be further improved with sensor fusion: using IMUs and encoders on top of our undrifting visual odometry increases precision between poles, and distance sensors help with exact alignment directly in front of poles.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="code" /><category term="robotics" /><summary type="html">The problem: Our robot needs to precisely navigate a field of poles.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">really bad Gilgamesh scifi fanfiction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/story/2022/10/02/gigamesh.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="really bad Gilgamesh scifi fanfiction" /><published>2022-10-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-10-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/story/2022/10/02/gigamesh</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/story/2022/10/02/gigamesh.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Space Epic of Gilgamesh&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A worn-out interceptor floats alone in the outskirts of the Cosmic Café parking lot, its rusty, bullet-hole-littered frame dimly reflecting the neon glow from the faraway restaurant. An ancient mercenary sits gloomily in the cockpit. Gilgamesh, veteran of the Great Plutonic Wars, is drinking to forget. His glory days were gone; his pay, gone. Just fired from his last job, he’s all by himself this lonely night; Struggling to shake out the last drops of moonshine; His rocky body, whose inertia had crushed Charonian armor, now too heavy to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thundering jolt shakes Gilgamesh out of his slumber. Out to the left of his window, a blue Spacefarer had crashed into his interceptor. Gilgamesh curses in rage and climbs out of the cockpit. He leaps onto the intruding ship and drags out its pilot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Who the hell are you to ram into my ship like that?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m gravely sorry, sir. I’m Enkidu, I’m just a poor worker here. I was just drivin’ to work my night shift—”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You know how much this ship costs? And you, just goddamn slams into it like a blind latel!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m sorry but I didn’t see any lights on you. And my headlight’s broken too. Please, it’s all an accident. And I’m a poor man, you see. I’ve got no money to pay—”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh you’re goddamn payin’ all right! You’re not leavin’ here til you do.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh please. Look what junk I have! I swear I’ve got no money on me besides a few coins. You want pay? Your ass has better chances picking on Humbaba!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, a very crappy transition to exposition of Humbaba&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The hell’s that?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Livin’ under a rock this past decade? There’s a monster who took over one of the planets the Plutonians nuked. Humbar, ’bout as big as Mercury, was earmarked for mining before the war. But during the Siege of Dove, our commander decided to scorch the Earth rather than let the Charons have it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That bastard.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That Humbar’s so rich in transuranium it could power a thousand tankers for a century each. But now, this freakin’ mountain-sized megaorganism roams its shores!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well then, if you know so much, go defeat it and pay me.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You crazy? Hundreds have tried! The army even sent an expeditionary force once. But Humbaba guards Humbar like a black hole. No one’s ever returned.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t care. You wronged me and you need to goddamn pay.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh bloody hell! Look at you! You’re a warrior! You’ve been through some real shit. I’ve done fights in the asteroid slums but hell if I have to kill an actual monster. Want money to bandage up your junk of a warship? Go fight Humbaba yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Don’t want to pay eh?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a moment Gilgamesh relents. But he still feels injustice boiling in his veins. A need to punish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fine, you wuss. But you’re guiding me there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he hauls Enkidu onboard the interceptor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They head to Humbar at full speed. In 3 Sols they’ve reached the planet of no return. In 3 Sols, Enkidu had chatted up Gilgamesh, and they now at least accept each other’s presence. Now the purple planet is hovering above their heads. The monster, a slithering mass, occasionally peaks its head above the clouds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They de-orbit into Humbar’s atmosphere. For three minutes their ship violently shakes as it plunges into thick air for the first time in a year. The pungent smell of a beast’s breath diffuses into the recharging life support system. The engine cut out a minute too early, and Gilgamesh crash-landed his craft into a mudpool a kilometer behind the monster’s back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ve awaken Humbaba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its tail unfurls itself across the plains. Sweeping a giant arc before them, it ignites a chain of sonic booms that knocks the ship on its side. Gilgamesh and Enkidu hurriedly climb out, plasma pikes in  one hand, neutronium shields in the other. Enkidu frightened, but Gilgamesh determined, to fight this monster and claim the riches to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humbaba’s ears notice the irregularities in the shockwaves’ echo. She turns her head, slowly scanning across the horizon. But the men know they have been found. By the time she spots their spacecraft, they’re running straight towards her head. Humbaba snarls. They lunge at her with all their might. But Humbaba makes a great meow, and transforms into a winged cat. She lifts into the air and stomps down at the two men. They block with their shields, but their bodies are compressed to the extreme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just when Humbaba thought the men have been killed, Enkidu rolls out from under and spears her eyes. Gilgamesh ran up her back and slits her neck. With a great, deafening sound Humbaba fell onto the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A monster destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be continued. (by Shin?)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="story" /><summary type="html">The Space Epic of Gilgamesh</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Curtain</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/art/pixel/2021/09/05/curtain.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Curtain" /><published>2021-09-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/art/pixel/2021/09/05/curtain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/art/pixel/2021/09/05/curtain.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/curtain-w1000.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mie scattering&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outlines are funny. You cut out a square, but then it begin folding into itself and all hell breaks loose.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="art" /><category term="pixel" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mie</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/art/pixel/2021/08/25/mie.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mie" /><published>2021-08-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/art/pixel/2021/08/25/mie</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/art/pixel/2021/08/25/mie.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/mie-w1024.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mie scattering&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rayleigh–Taylor instabilities project themselves onto the great wispy clouds. Two figures stand against on dark soil.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="art" /><category term="pixel" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>