<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-20T03:05:26-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">{ xing liu ∘ 刘行 }</title><subtitle>local thoughtspace of a possible boltzmann brain in awe of the cosmic infinite</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The background of the universe</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/astro/2023/12/19/medium.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The background of the universe" /><published>2023-12-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/astro/2023/12/19/medium</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/astro/2023/12/19/medium.html">&lt;p&gt;When we try to picture the cosmos, we tend to only think about the shiny stuff — 
stars, galaxies, and very very hungry black holes. But stars cannot burn their hearts without cold hydrogen to collapse from,
cannot coalesce into galaxies without dark matter to pull them together, and cannot shine as black holes after death without more gas and dust to feed on.
The background medium, as it turns out, has as much tremendous importance to astronomy as the objects underneath the spotlights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with our home galaxy, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milky_Way&quot;&gt;Milky Way&lt;/a&gt;. 
There are approximately a hundred billion (10¹¹) stars bound in its gravitational system, 
collectively weighing around 10¹¹ Suns (our Sun is pretty average — in astronomy we call that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stellar_classification&quot;&gt;G tier&lt;/a&gt;). 
According to our current model of stellar evolution, 
every single one of them started out as a loose (one might even say &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nebula&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;nebulous&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) cloud of gas and dust,
contracting for millions of years until their core reaches the critical temperature for nuclear fusion to occur. Then, after anywhere
from millions to billions of years, they exhaust all their fuel, and through either a gentle winding-down or a spectacular explosion,
return most of their matter back into the medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the births and deaths of stars roughly balance, it leaves around 10¹¹ Suns’ worth of gas and dust hanging around inside the galaxy,
on the same order of magnitude as the collective mass of the stars themselves. 
As expected, we mainly find those gas and dust in the thin, flat central slice of the Milky Way disk, which is also where most of the young stars live.
(Including our Sun, which explains why we can’t really see the center of our galaxy — the pesky dust blocks the line of sight.)
Its cosmic cycle between loosely-bound clouds and dense, burning stars forms the basis of the galactic ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have stars, we need a way to put them into a galaxy. 
You might think that, mirroring our Sun’s role in the solar system, 
having a super massive black hole at the galactic center would be enough to hold everything together.
Unfortunately, Sagitarrius A*, the super massive black hole in the core of the Milky Way, just isn’t supermassive enough!
While the Sun holds over 99.8% of the mass of the solar system, 
Sagitarrius A*, weighing at a measly several million Suns, is less than 0.01% of the mass of the Milky Way.
Adding the bulge of stars, gas, and dust clustered around Sag A* doesn’t make that big of a dent either.
For galaxies to form, there has to be a lot of extra mass concentrated near the center that we’ve so far not accounted for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the stuff we call &lt;em&gt;dark matter&lt;/em&gt;. We don’t really know what it’s made of, but for it to hold galaxies together
and explain a bunch of other cosmological mysteries, we know it has to satisify a few properties:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[work in progress article!]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;em&gt;interstellar medium&lt;/em&gt; (ISM) — the stuff between stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s just the stuff inside galaxies. If the distance between neighboring stars is vast 
(it takes light more than 4 years to travel from here to Alpha Centauri), 
the distance between neighboring galaxies is truly cosmic. And between galaxy neighborhoods? incomprehensible.
Inside galaxies, the medium and the stars are roughly balanced. Out in the intergalactic wilderness, the wispy medium is nearly all there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as there’s far more grass on the plains than sheep, and far more water in the seas than fish, the full background 
medium of the universe actually far, &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; outweighs the stars! 
We believe as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This medium contains loose gas, dust, and most mysteriously, &lt;em&gt;dark matter&lt;/em&gt;. (more to come)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="astro" /><summary type="html">When we try to picture the cosmos, we tend to only think about the shiny stuff — stars, galaxies, and very very hungry black holes. But stars cannot burn their hearts without cold hydrogen to collapse from, cannot coalesce into galaxies without dark matter to pull them together, and cannot shine as black holes after death without more gas and dust to feed on. The background medium, as it turns out, has as much tremendous importance to astronomy as the objects underneath the spotlights.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">December 2023</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/monthly/2023/12/18/monthly.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="December 2023" /><published>2023-12-18T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/monthly/2023/12/18/monthly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/monthly/2023/12/18/monthly.html">&lt;p&gt;decision paralysis but also, &lt;br /&gt;
recognizing in a finite lifespan I &lt;br /&gt;
get to pick a few things out of an &lt;br /&gt;
infinitude to savor is kinda neat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;如果有桂花吃、白兰花闻，世界就好了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;current trajectory: physics &amp;gt; cosmology/particle &amp;gt; theoretical/computational&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deniz Türker. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psupress.org/books/titles/978-0-271-09391-8.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Accidental Palace: The Making of Yıldız in Nineteenth-Century Istanbul&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The residence of the last Ottoman sultan before his empire’s fall.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Tong. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.damtp.cam.ac.uk/user/tong/gaugetheory.html&quot;&gt;“Lecture notes on Gauge Theory.”&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Every once in a while, I try to get a glimpse of some topic years beyond my current level of understanding. 
Two years ago it was general relativity, last summer it was inflationary cosmology, and last week it was gauge theory 
— basically, fields in which the concepts and equations nearly completely lose me. 
Even though I am not really ready to efficiently learn these topics, I think it’s helpful to have a somewhat tangible sense of the long road ahead.
With this goal in mind, I began reading and promptly lost myself by the second chapter.
I did manage to make a video out of it though.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matthew McQuinn. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-astro-082214-122355&quot;&gt;“The Evolution of the Intergalactic Medium.”&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When we try to picture the cosmos, we tend to only think about the shiny stuff — stars, galaxies, and very very hungry black holes. But stars cannot burn their hearts without cold hydrogen to collapse from, cannot coalesce into galaxies without dark matter to pull them together, and cannot shine as black holes after death without more gas and dust to feed on. The background medium, as it turns out, has as much tremendous importance to astronomy as the objects underneath the spotlights…
&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/astro/2023/12/19/medium.html&quot;&gt;“The stuff between all the universe’s bright lights.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cade Metz et al. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/12/03/technology/ai-openai-musk-page-altman.html&quot;&gt;“Ego, Fear and Money: How the A.I. Fuse Was Lit”&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;These people have strange sights for the future.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="monthly" /><summary type="html">decision paralysis but also, recognizing in a finite lifespan I get to pick a few things out of an infinitude to savor is kinda neat</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A rough sketch of gauge theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/physics/animation/2023/12/08/gauge.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A rough sketch of gauge theory" /><published>2023-12-08T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/physics/animation/2023/12/08/gauge</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/physics/animation/2023/12/08/gauge.html">&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vEN4uXE8rkg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very rough introduction to one of the building blocks of modern theoretical particle physics,
starting with its humble origins in the field of classical electrodynamics, 
and showing how this almost “redundant” description of electromagnetism 
grew into the language with which physicists think about the fundamental nature of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="physics" /><category term="animation" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">November 2023</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/monthly/2023/11/20/monthly.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="November 2023" /><published>2023-11-20T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/monthly/2023/11/20/monthly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/monthly/2023/11/20/monthly.html">&lt;p&gt;in summary, month of reading too many things&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;red,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helliwell &amp;amp; Sahakian. Modern Classical Mechanics.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;God-tier capstone chapters offering us lowly undergrads glimpses of quantum path integrals, gauge invariance, perturbation theory, among other &lt;em&gt;fascinating&lt;/em&gt; areas of modern physics&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lindner. A Complete Guide to Theoretical Physics.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The promise in the title is the allure.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leslie Pierce. The Imperial Harem: Women and sovereignty in the Ottoman Empire.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The struggles for power never bores&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Benjamin Fortna. Imperial Classrooms: Islam, the State, and Education in the Late Ottoman Empire.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Maps!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Benedict Anderson. Imagined Communities.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The&lt;/strong&gt; book on nationalism.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amy Tan. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2000/12/25/immortal-heart&quot;&gt;“Immortal Heart”&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Read it on the night bart from San Jose back to Berkeley. How little time I’m devoting to fiction!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thomas Mallon. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2023/11/27/yesterday-a-new-history-of-nostalgia-tobias-becker-book-review&quot;&gt;“What if Nostalgia Isn’t What It Used to Be?”&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="monthly" /><summary type="html">in summary, month of reading too many things</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AdS-CFT</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/physics/2023/11/04/adscft.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AdS-CFT" /><published>2023-11-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-11-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/physics/2023/11/04/adscft</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/physics/2023/11/04/adscft.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/ads-cft-w1011.png&quot; alt=&quot;ADS-CFT&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;hyperbolic tilings are so cool&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the way this is going, geometry might be both my first and last subject in math.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="physics" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cracks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/art/pastel/2023/10/06/cracks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cracks" /><published>2023-10-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-10-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/art/pastel/2023/10/06/cracks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/art/pastel/2023/10/06/cracks.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/cracks-w2696.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cracks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offering shade to the skies in the dead of night.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="art" /><category term="pastel" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is the Hubble Tension?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/astro/2023/09/02/tension.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is the Hubble Tension?" /><published>2023-09-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-09-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/astro/2023/09/02/tension</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/astro/2023/09/02/tension.html">&lt;p&gt;Work in progress&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Converting from slideshow&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overviews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carroll, S.M. Spacetime and Geometry (2004)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Liddle, A. An Introduction to Modern Cosmology, 3e (2015)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seife, C. ‘Tired-Light’ Hypothesis Gets Re-Tired. Science (2021)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Essinger-Hileman, T.M. et al. Hubble Constant. NASA Lambda (2021)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ananthaswamy, A. Astronomers Gear Up to Grapple with the High-Tension Cosmos. Scientific American (2022)
Research articles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jedamzik, K. et al. Why reducing the cosmic sound horizon alone can not fully resolve the Hubble tension. Commun Phys 4 (2021)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oppenheimer, J.R. et al. On Massive Neutron Cores. Physical Review 55, 4 (1939)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Riess, A.G. et al.  A Comprehensive Measurement of the Local Value of the Hubble Constant. ApJL 934, 1 (2021)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Addison, G.E. et al. Cosmological constraints from BAOs and clustering of LSS. MNRAS, 436, 2 (2013)
Images&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Budassi, P.C. CMB sphere mapped by ESA and Planck collaboration. Wikimedia Commons (2020)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keel, W.C. The Road to Galaxy Formation, 2e (2007)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gutierrez, A.M. James Webb Space Telescope rendering. (2022)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="astro" /><summary type="html">Work in progress</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Redshift surveys</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/astro/2023/08/28/desi.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Redshift surveys" /><published>2023-08-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/astro/2023/08/28/desi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/astro/2023/08/28/desi.html">&lt;p&gt;Watching fly-throughs of galaxy maps reminds me of shining a flashlight in a dusty room; 
the illuminated particles, each clinging on tight to its own little world of unfathomably many tiny creatures, dance chaotically on the dark undercurrents of air. 
By observing their Brownian motion, Einstein was able to deduce the atomic nature of the unseen medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hundred years later, with galaxies suspended in spacetime, might we be able to do the same thing?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="astro" /><summary type="html">Watching fly-throughs of galaxy maps reminds me of shining a flashlight in a dusty room; the illuminated particles, each clinging on tight to its own little world of unfathomably many tiny creatures, dance chaotically on the dark undercurrents of air. By observing their Brownian motion, Einstein was able to deduce the atomic nature of the unseen medium.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Decanting</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/art/pastel/2023/08/12/decanting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decanting" /><published>2023-08-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-08-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/art/pastel/2023/08/12/decanting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/art/pastel/2023/08/12/decanting.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/decanting-w1909.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Decanting&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accretion disks make for fun ruffs&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="art" /><category term="pastel" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes on Carroll &amp;amp; Ostlie, Introduction to Modern Astrophysics, parts I &amp;amp; II</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/notes/astro/2023/07/20/notes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Carroll &amp;amp; Ostlie, Introduction to Modern Astrophysics, parts I &amp;amp; II" /><published>2023-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2023-07-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/notes/astro/2023/07/20/notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/notes/astro/2023/07/20/notes.html">&lt;p&gt;My notes for the first two parts of Carroll &amp;amp; Ostlie’s “Big Orange Book”, 
written in a combination of markdown and LaTeX for the optimal mix of 
accessibility and mathematical typographic beauty, are available at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://xingyzt.net/notes/intro-to-modern-astrophysics&quot;&gt;xingyzt.net/notes/intro-to-modern-astrophysics&lt;/a&gt;. 
Enjoy studying the universe!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="notes" /><category term="astro" /><summary type="html">My notes for the first two parts of Carroll &amp;amp; Ostlie’s “Big Orange Book”, written in a combination of markdown and LaTeX for the optimal mix of accessibility and mathematical typographic beauty, are available at xingyzt.net/notes/intro-to-modern-astrophysics. Enjoy studying the universe!</summary></entry></feed>